this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
ski radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society IEEE software Magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
welcome to software engineering's ATO
I'm your host brijesh amanat and today
my guest is George Duty Josh is a former
electrical engineer known project
manager and consultant he's author of
multiple books including Fearless salary
negotiation and mastering business email
Josh is a salary negotiation coach who
works with high earners to negotiate job
offers Josh welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything I
missed in your bio that you'd like to
add
hi thanks for having me it's really good
to be here no I think that's a really
good summary I think you got everything
in there that felt really good thanks
Josh is a repeat guest having spoken to
us about salary negotiation in episode
275. today we will be talking about
business communication Josh can you
start by explaining what is business
communication and how is it different
from other forms of communication
yeah I mean in a lot of ways you know
communication is communication so I
could talk about differences and I could
talk about similarities I think business
communication though when I think about
communication the first thing I think
about is you know the reason for the
communication what are we trying to
communicate and in business usually
trying to communicate something to help
move some sort of a business objective
forward assuming that it's not you know
small talk or something like that
instead it's you know an email that says
hey can you give me a status update or
can you help me understand what the
purpose of this project is and so
usually business communication is
focused on you know how do we move a
business objective forward and that's
the purpose of the communication as
opposed to all those other thing I
mentioned so I think that business
communication is focused on the business
whereas other types of communication
could be for any reason which might not
even have a meaning other than just
communicating so it's focused there's a
reason for it there's something that
we're trying to accomplish with business
communication right and in your
experience have you seen people use the
personal communication design in a
business setting and what have been the
consequences you know I have I think
sometimes it is pretty effective
especially when there's a big difference
between sort of like the person's level
in an organization with the other person
they're talking to I think it can help
to be more personal so you know if I
happen to bump into the CEO of a big
company in the hallway I think it's
really helpful if the CEO is a
personable person who's able to talk
casually and that could be beneficial to
the working structure of the working
environment whereas for people who are
closer together sometimes being a little
bit too personal can obfuscate what the
purpose of the communication is and can
actually slow things down so in other
words you know if a manager and their
direct report are communicating in a way
that's too personal direct report might
not understand the urgency of a
situation or might not understand the
criticality of a thing that needs to be
accomplished because it sounds like just
a friendly request or communication and
so I think there are positive and
negative things that can come from more
personal versus more professional type
communication Styles but when I think of
the personal I think it can be really
helpful in settings where there's a big
gap in the org chart between two people
and they're not trying to accomplish
something specifically business oriented
whereas of course if the CEO is
communicating with the company in an all
hands meeting or something more
professional is usually better in my
opinion directed at the objective so
that there's no confusions so that
everybody's on the same page right so
like most things in life context matters
and it depends on where and whom you're
talking to and what are you trying to
achieve out of that conversation yes
that's a great summary you summarized it
better than what I said no not really
we'll move into the next section where
we'll dig deeper into the various
communication Styles and modes of
communication and we'll let's start off
with meetings what are the various types
of meetings and how does one gauge
what's expected from a meeting when you
get the invite
yeah you know they're probably sort of
an infinite number of types of meetings
but in general you know even zooming out
if I am scheduling a meeting with
someone first of all before I do that I
want to make sure that I can articulate
what the purpose of the meeting is
regardless of what the format or medium
is and I think that's pretty important I
know you know I'm kind of easy to find
on the internet and so people reach out
to me pretty frequently asking for
meetings and it really helps me to know
when they say hey do you have some time
to chat if they can say why so that I
understand the purpose so the first
thing is with any meeting regardless of
the medium or the location I think it's
important to just have a specific reason
for that meeting in mind time is really
valuable especially in engineering where
flow is a really important thing you
want to have your schedule disrupted as
little as possible if you're trying to
get into flow and so I think that if I'm
requesting a meeting or someone else is
requesting a meeting that it's important
that the purpose of the meeting be sort
of stated up front as far as the types
of meetings you know if my mind first
goes to individual like one-on-one
meetings and group meetings prepping for
those is much different I think you know
the more people that you have in a
meeting then the more important it is to
make sure that each one of those people
has some purpose for being there similar
to you know articulating the purpose for
a meeting up front when you're asking
for it it's also important to say well
I've invited you know 17 people to a
meeting do they need to be there and
they're wondering the same thing so
that's the second thing is you know is
everybody on this attendee list really
needed to be in the meeting in
understanding that the fact that they're
attending the meeting means they're not
doing something else so there's an
opportunity cost to them being in the
meeting and I think it's important at
any level of the organization to think
about this so what I mean by that is you
know sometimes newer employees will not
really think through that at all and
they'll say oh I have a question I'll
just schedule a meeting with these 10
people and not realizing that they're
literally claiming you know thousands of
dollars of time of value to have a
meeting without thinking through like is
it necessary that all these people be
there and the flip side a lot of senior
people and organizations sort of just
dismissed the effort that it takes for
someone to stop what they're doing and
attend a meeting for them and so they'll
just kind of broadcast a big meeting
invite to a bunch of people without
thinking you know is it worth it
disrupting all of these people's work so
that they can come to this meeting so
again this all comes back to you know
what is the purpose of the meeting for
the different formats once you've
decided you know who actually needs to
be in this meeting whose time is it
worth spending in this meeting then
you've got your sort of classic phone
meetings right you've got a
teleconference basically where a lot of
people call into a phone call you've got
your Zoom meetings now is you know I
think becoming dominant where it's you
know face to face and then you've got
sort of your in-person kind of meeting
in a conference room or something like
that and I think again each one of those
has a purpose I think it's this is maybe
a side quest but I think it's a little
bit unfortunate that Zoom has become so
popular and that people just want to
kind of default to like a video meeting
and the reason for that is that through
my career whenever I'm in a meeting
sometimes I'm able to multitask and I
know that can be kind of frowned upon
but Zoom essentially requires especially
if your camera is on it requires you to
be kind of artificially focused on a
specific thing which means that your
mind cannot be doing anything else even
if you are not even required at that
moment in the meeting so if it's an
hour-long meeting and I'm on camera the
whole time and I've got five minutes of
responsibility people might be
frustrated when they see me looking down
at my desk or check out my email or
something like that and so Zoom is an
interesting hybrid where I think it can
kind of close the gap geographically but
also it can make it really difficult for
people to actually do other things and
they're sort of stuck whereas if I'm on
the phone you can't see my face I'll
frequently be multitasking I'm not right
now by the way but I'll be multitasking
because it's Audio Only and you you
can't see me so those are the three
meeting types and again I think it's
important to think about what's the
necessity for the particular medium that
we're using here and I'll give an
example of I was talking to a CEO let's
call it a software education company
maybe six weeks ago and we're chatting
in slack and both of us agreed
simultaneously hey you know what we
should just talk on the phone this is
too nuanced a conversation to have in
asynchronous text and so we jump on a
phone call but first I was like do you
want to zoom or you want a phone call
he's like oh I want a phone call because
I pace and I was like yes me too meaning
you know I'm if you looked at me from
the outside while I'm on the phone with
this person you might think that I'm
totally distracted because I'm wandering
around my house and I'm like picking
stuff up in my office and you know
playing with fidget Spinners and stuff
but the reality is that's how I'm
focusing on that person and what they're
saying to me so I can really internalize
the words that they're saying and so the
freedom of a audio only phone call is
pretty beneficial there because I can
really focus on the context and content
of our conversation rather than focusing
on you know am I making good eye contact
with the camera does it look like I'm
really dialed in in focused how's my
lighting and all that stuff so that's a
really long answer to your question but
I think that the three mediums I think
of our Audio Only in person conference
room and then the sort of hybrid Zoom
meeting where you're on camera most of
the time you've touched on some very
interesting points and we will double
click into them the primarily the
virtual meetings as with a slack but
before that I do want to ask some
generic questions around meetings so one
of the most challenging situations that
one finds in a meeting is where you have
to deal with disagreements what's a good
way to deal with disagreements in a
meeting
oh that's a really good question I mean
I can talk a lot about it I mean I
really believe I probably could write a
book on that and there probably are
books written on it but I'll give you my
kind of general principles for
disagreements first of all I generally
assume that when there's a disagreement
that both of the disagreeing parties
have honest reasons for disagreeing so
in other words I'm assuming that people
are not trying to sabotage each other
this is a healthy working environment
and so what that means is there's a
disagreement what it means is that the
people just have a different vision for
how the things should be accomplished or
what the purpose of the activity might
be or even just the data that they're
looking at and so that's my Baseline is
you know we have an honest disagreement
here we both just have a different
perspective on this thing and because of
that I think the way to approach that is
is with the sort of positive approach
and so this is something that I've
thought a lot about and that I I teach
people in the courses that I make and
that is using positive language and sort
of a positive perspective on the
communication that you're having so if
there's a disagreement the first thing I
do is try to find a common ground right
and also I look for an opportunity to
say listen I disagree with you on this
but I think that you've done a great job
with whatever and so that could be yes I
disagree with you on the data that we're
looking at and I think that you've done
a great job with Gathering the data and
in terms operating it and I think that
we just fundamentally disagree on what
the interpretation of the data is but
that doesn't mean that either of us is
necessarily wrong it could just mean
that there are different implications
for what we're looking at so I'm looking
for the positive spin on the
disagreement so and the reason to do
that is very tactical it's because when
we can agree on something even if it's
that we both are doing this in good
faith then we can collaborate better to
come to a solution to the disagreement
because by definition the disagreement
is sort of an impasse it means that
either somebody's going to have to pull
rank or we're going to have to convince
one or the other person that their
perspective is the right perspective or
find a common solution that is a
different a third perspective that may
not be either of their perspectives but
to do that you have to be able to
collaborate and so the alternative would
be coming at the disagreement saying I
think you're doing this in bad faith or
just having a bad attitude about it and
that's essentially going to block
progress what that means is if you take
that perspective on a disagreement
you're going to continue to have a
disagreement which is not really
conducive to moving forward in a
business sense so the first thing is to
find a positive commonality to
understand the person's perspective the
best you can to recognize that they've
probably put some work into their
opinion and then to start pursuing a
common ground to resolve the
disagreement in general resolving
disagreements I mean there are literal
books written on this and it's a very
difficult topic but I think that the
most important thing for business
context type disagreements is to zoom
out and to look at you know what is our
Top Line goal kpis you know whatever you
want to call them but we should be
discussing something that somehow
contributes to what the company or the
team or the business unit is trying to
accomplish so first let's agree on what
the thing is that we're trying to
accomplish and then let's see if we can
figure out a way out of disagreement to
get to a thing that helps us us to
accomplish that goal and so I think that
is a good way to avoid sort of personal
level disagreements to avoid vilifying
the counterparty that you're disagreeing
with and instead to focus on what's the
common thing that we're trying to
accomplish here and how do we get to
that thing and I think that will help
kind of guide our way out of
disagreements in a way that's
collaborative so that we can say okay
well we do agree that we're trying to
accomplish this business objective right
yes okay great so let's figure out how
we get on the same page to accomplish
that as opposed to I'm going to convince
you that you're wrong or you're going to
convince me that I'm wrong or I'm just
going to berate you because I think
you're an idiot and that kind of stuff
that's not productive it doesn't help
you accomplish those goals instead you
become people on the same team with the
same objective to help accomplish that
kpi and then you can move forward and
say well let's find a way out of this
disagreement into a common solution that
helps us to accomplish the goal that we
set out to accomplish when we started
this conversation some very important
points over there and I like the point
where you said that at the end of the
day it's about a business school that
both people in the conversation want to
achieve so it's important not to make it
a personal conversation rather continue
to focus on the business objective and
then zoom out to see what the different
Viewpoint is
the other challenging situation that
I've found quite a lot of times and
meetings is dominant personalities
taking over the meeting and having an
opinion on everything which means that
it's difficult to finish a meeting on
time or reach conclusions
how do you manage or handle dominant
Personalities in a meeting this can be
really challenging it's a very specific
skill set and so I have kind of two
categories of ways to handle this sort
of thing in my mind one of them is sort
of on the personal level and that is
ultimately the person who is sort of the
dominant personality needs to be aware
of that and that usually probably would
come from a manager or somebody who's
their peer to say Hey you seem to be
kind of running over this meeting and I
appreciate your input
however what that means is that there
are people who are definitely not
speaking up who have good things to say
and so that's kind of the first thing is
sort of the root cause of that it's
usually so the way that you described it
I would say there's probably a person
who has sort of an outsized perspective
on how much influence they should have
in the meeting and they might be
inadvertently sort of stifling other
points of view and then I would also say
so that's the the personality type thing
right and the flip side would be
encouraging the people who are sort of
less verbal who are less aggressive to
say Hey you know your input is valued
and we would like to hear what you have
to say which is again another kind of a
personal thing so you want to kind of
try and bring the volume of the
contributions down from the more
dominant personalities and sort of
increase the volume of contributions
from the less dominant personalities and
you can do that through encouraging them
to move both ways so you know when I was
a manager there were people who I knew
probably had good ideas but we're not
speaking up and so I would ask them
specifically like hey you know before we
wrap this topic do you have any input
here because I know that you probably
think pretty deeply about this and this
is you know frankly that's how I am most
of the time even in my friend group and
personally in my life but also in
business settings a lot of times there
will be a really intense conversation
going on and I have a lot of thoughts on
it but I'm the kind of person who I
would sort of sit back and observe
what's happening see what the other
people's thoughts are and start to kind
of process their thoughts while I'm
trying to figure out what I think about
this difficult topic I'm assuming that
we're talking about difficult topics
because otherwise kind of what's the
point but on those difficult topics I'll
frequently be quiet but I have very
strong opinions and what I'm doing is
letting the other people sort of hash
out how they feel about it get to a
place and then a lot of times my friends
will turn to look at me and say what do
you think about this and then I'll have
a very specific you know 15 second
thought that's a good summary of how I
feel and they'll go huh and it's a it's
a nice contribution but I have to be
given that window a lot of times because
I'm not going to assert myself into a
conversation where dominant people are
dominating but in a business setting
through training and just through
interpersonal communication you can kind
of encourage those people who are more
dominant to say Hey you know just make
sure that you leave some room in the
room for these other perspectives to
come into play and then for the less
dominant people to say Hey you know it's
okay for you to speak up I know that you
have good ideas and we want to hear what
you say also the last thing I'll say is
sort of from that kind of personal
perspective is if you are leading a
meeting like that I think it's okay to
allow silence it can be very
uncomfortable when you're leading a
meeting to ask a question and then you
don't get an immediate response and so
my kind of rule of thumb here when you
want thoughtful responses from people is
to give them about twice as long to
speak up as you think feels comfortable
as the person leading the meeting so if
you ask a question and you know there
are seven people in the room you ask a
question you don't get a response and
you start to feel uncomfortable from
that moment on restart the clock on
however long it took you to feel
uncomfortable and allow that much time
again so that those people who are more
quiet and might be kind of turning the
wheel slowly or less inclined to speak
up might have an opportunity to speak up
because eventually they will speak up
but a lot of times they're kind of
waiting to see if the the space is clear
for them to speak up and hopefully you
know again through encouraging those
people who are more dominant those
people might not speak up right the
people who always have something to say
might say you know maybe I could just be
quiet in this in this instance so that's
the personal side of it the other side
is sort of a structural side right so
the way that you organize the meeting I
think can help to encourage this sort of
thing and so having a very clear agenda
with very clear objectives with time
boxing can help a lot it'll help you
know for example if you segment five
minutes per topic and you know that
you're coming to five minutes and a good
a good person leading meeting will say
we're trying to stay on agenda here
we've got two minutes left on this I
just wanted to call that out and that
way the people who haven't spoken up yet
are encouraged to speak up because
they're the clock is running out they've
only got two minutes and it also kind of
reminds the people who have a lot to say
and are very verbose that maybe they
should kind of take it easy for the last
minute or two of this segment and let
other people speak up but it also helps
to keep the topics and the agenda moving
so that you don't end up with one per
person talking for 18 minutes on a topic
that was supposed to take two minutes
but nobody put anything into an agenda
so there's no way to really enforce that
so there's the the personal side
encouraging the dominant people to be
less dominant encouraging the quieter
people to speak up more
um allowing space for them to speak up
especially just allowing silence to
happen so that those quieter people will
will feel a little bit more courage and
speak up and then there's a structural
thing of actually structuring the
meeting with a good agenda and leading
the meeting well there is there should
be a person who is responsible for
leading the beating and that person is
in charge of the agenda and they can
help to keep the conversation moving and
even help to redirect and like I said
ask specific people to speak up and say
Hey you know Frank I know that you have
some good ideas around this we haven't
heard what you have to say we've got two
minutes left on this topic what do you
think and maybe Frank will say something
really profound that he wouldn't have
said otherwise if other people were
dominating the conversation so those are
my thoughts on kind of how to keep that
going and to make sure that you hear
input from everybody in a meeting very
useful and I'm definitely going to use
your rule of thumb which is wait for
twice the time it got you to feel
uncomfortable before breaking the
silence and calling out somebody or you
putting your own thoughts and I think
that's a very good rule of thumb yeah
thanks it you know I've led a lot of
meetings I think you mentioned early on
you know that I was a I don't know if
you mentioned that but I was a project
manager for a long time working on you
know a small to be in business and
Enterprise software implementations and
so a lot of times I would have a lot of
stakeholders in meetings and I've let a
lot of other meetings of course and it's
I think it's really important to leave
that space and it's you know as the
person attending the meeting you're
thinking Hmm how do I feel about that
and you're trying to formulate thoughts
and all this good stuff and then but as
the person leading to me and you're like
oh man silence is bad people are going
to tune out they're going to stop
listening but really the clock in your
head is probably ticking a lot faster
than anyone else because you're
responsible for the meeting being
productive and so that's why I kind of
created that rule of thumb for myself is
if you double that time from when you
feel uncomfortable that's probably about
the right amount of time to allow
violence to indicate that okay people
actually don't have anything to say here
as opposed to their formulating thoughts
or trying to you know gather the courage
to speak up so I like it as a rule of
thumb and it works great for me great
we'll move on to take a bit deeper into
virtual Communications considering it's
so prevalent now with remote working and
you've already touched on zoom and the
way you know people use it so maybe
we'll start off knowing your thoughts on
what are the some good rules of thumb or
what's a good etiquette to follow when
you're on video conference or a virtual
meeting yeah first of all it's really
interesting because we've done
especially with um once a pandemic
happened and everybody moved to zoom
we've kind of all collectively moved to
these video meetings and I've been doing
them for probably 10 years in different
capacities with Google Hangouts and zoom
and other other media however I think
this is still kind of emergent so I'm
not sure there's a there's a great
answer here yet I think we're trying to
figure it out I think a couple of things
one is I do think that it's important
that if you're going to have your camera
on that it I don't think you necessarily
have to be looking into the camera at
all times but I think that it's
important to not be doing stuff that's
distracting any kind of movement right
like our our brains are trained to to
identify movement in our vicinity so
that we can respond to it that's just
how we interact with our world and so
the the really interesting thing about
Zoom is you know you have you know 10
tiles on your screen and everybody's
doing their own thing with different
lighting and stuff and you can see
people moving and it's just very
distracting and so you know one thing is
just you know if you're going to be on
camera try to be present there and if
you're not just mute your camera if you
can right just turn it off it's much
better if you're not going to be
speaking and you're going to be
fidgeting or moving around or messing
with stuff in the background that can be
really distracting to people and so I
would say just just turn your camera off
I think also like it helps to have good
lighting if you can and that could
literally just be a desk lamp that you
turn on in front of you so that your
face is lit so that people can see you a
lot of our communication is kind of
visual body language type communication
unfortunately you don't get a real
version of that on Zoom because it's
this artificial like I'm just looking at
your face whereas I would you know for
example if you and I were talking face
to face probably like 30 percent of the
time we would actually look at each
other in the eye and the rest of the
time you know we would be looking off or
you know looking at somebody's shoulder
or you know looking down at my hand or
or something like that like we just look
around when we talk but if you do that
on Zoom it feels really weird so I do
think that you should facilitate you
know people seeing what they can see
with good lighting and like I said if
you're on camera be on camera for a
purpose and if you're going to be
fidgeting turn your camera off and I
also think that it really helps to not
be making a lot of noise on Zoom calls
this is true for all conference calls
but people can tend to sort of default
to I'll have my camera on I'll just
leave myself unmuted and then there you
can hear them wrestling papers on their
desk so anything that's that's confusing
or that's distracting I think try to
eliminate it I think this is
particularly true for Zoom because
there's already so much distraction so
if I'm on a zoom call like I said with
10 tiles on the screen there's already a
lot coming at me and if even one person
person is fidgeting around with
something that I can hear audibly that's
another distraction for me so the
general rule of thumb for Zoom meetings
for video meetings I would say is just
try to minimize distractions and make
sure that people on the call including
the host or whoever is talking can focus
so that's my kind of overall rule of
thumb for Zoom is just minimize
distractions also I would say you know
my second one is you know make sure that
again that everybody who's on this Zoom
meeting needs to be there because Zoom
meetings in particular when your camera
is on are maybe the least flexible way
to communicate meaning that if I'm on a
zoom meeting with my camera on for all
the reasons that I just mentioned that's
all I'm doing I'm sitting in front of my
camera even if I'm not talking even if
I'm not contributing that's what I'm
doing so you want to make sure that if
you've asked somebody to do that to
essentially focus on one thing and not
allow themselves to do anything else if
there's a reason for them to do that and
so you know if you're going to call a
zoom meeting if you're gonna have
multiple people in there just make sure
all the people should be there and this
is I think more critical than any other
medium because even in a conference room
I can I'm not looking at I can't see
everybody's face simultaneously I have
to turn my head to do that and so they
can be distracted taking notes or
whatever but on Zoom I can literally see
everybody's face looking back at me or
not looking back at me and it can be
very distracting so make sure that the
people who are there should be there
because that's a particularly restrict
form of communication having to sit in
front of a camera with a microphone and
you know appear to be attentive so
you're not distracting other people you
talked about taking notes I just want to
ask a question around that is it a good
practice to take notes and what do you
do of the notes where's the meeting
should you send it out to everybody with
actions or and who should be the person
responsible for doing that
yeah this is a good question I don't
know that there's a good answer and it's
probably going to be sort of based on
the company culture that you're working
with if possible so I think gosh this is
hard and here's why for me taking notes
as a distraction I don't do it unless I
absolutely have to do it the only time
that I take notes in a meeting is
basically if I'm going to somehow need
that material to prep for something else
and so for me taking notes is a
distraction because I will focus on
taking good notes and not on the content
and so I can kind of just turn my brain
off and turn the words that are being
said around me into notes on paper but I
won't actually be processing any of the
words that I hear so my preference in a
meeting is to have a designated Note
Taker who takes minutes or notes and
then sends them out to everybody and
says here's the notes from the meeting
obviously you do want to take notes if
there's something very specific to you
for example if you have an action item
or if there's some Nuance that you need
to write down that is relevant to your
particular function or responsibility
that a general Note Taker might not get
or a thought that you have have for
example that isn't public right like
it's in your brain you think oh yeah
this is a good idea I'll jot this down I
think that's good but I think in general
if possible having a specific person
responsible for taking the notes and
sending them out are good and what I
mean by that is you know what were the
topics that were discussed what were the
specific action items that were called
out that stuff I think is much better
left to a single person and you could
rotate that around or sometimes you'll
have a designated person or scribe you
know a lot of Physicians have a lot of
friends or Physicians they actually have
a function in hospitals and in other
places called a scribe and this person
Shadows the doctor and takes notes on
behalf of the doctor so the doctor can
interact with the patient one-on-one
give them their full attention and not
have to worry about whether or not
they're remembering everything or
getting all the notes right and so they
can be totally present with the patient
so I think that's a good model for for
meetings if possible where there's a
person who takes notes that person is
responsible for getting the high level
topics that were covered in a meeting
disseminating action items after the
meeting so that everyone else can engage
in the meeting itself so that everyone
else can just focus on the topic I will
say I think for some people taking notes
is the opposite of me I turn my brain
off and just try to write words down as
they come out I think other people
actually do process the information by
taking notes and I think that some
people will perceive that to be sort of
a distraction so if I'm in a meeting not
me personally but you know hypothetical
me is in a meeting and I see somebody
else taking notes I'm thinking they're
not really paying attention but that
person might actually be maximally
paying attention by taking notes so I
think allow leeway for personal
preference here I would say at a
business function sort of level that
having the ability to to just have a
note taker somebody who takes minutes
and action items is a really good idea
it frees everybody else up to actually
just have a discussion and a
conversation but I will say that's my
personal opinion that's how I do things
when I run meetings other people might
have different opinions and I wouldn't
say that I'm right and they're wrong
it's probably going to be personal
preference and maybe business culture
yeah I'll agree I must confess that I
fall into the latter part where I feel
like concentrate more and I'm able to
cross more if I'm taking notes because
it stops my mind from wandering and the
temptation to multitask gets reduced
because you're focusing on understanding
what's being said and noting it down
these important points that you need to
follow up on yeah which I think is very
valid right like I know a lot of people
that are that function exactly like you
just described that are just like you
where for me taking notes is a
distraction because I'm for whatever
reason my brain just tries to focus on
make sure these notes are good I want to
make sure I capture everything and I'm
not really actually thinking about the
words that are said whereas you are able
to focus in more because you're taking
notes you are processing the words and
you're not allowing other ideas or
thoughts or you know activities to come
to mind or you're not distracted by a
deliverable that you have tomorrow
because you're taking the notes so I
think there should be a lot of leeway
here in your business culture for people
with different preferences on this
sometimes I think there are things that
you kind of have to do as a matter of
rule and I think there are things where
it's personal preference that matters
and I think you know this is one of
those things where whatever makes the
individual most productive that's how
they should probably you know behave in
a meeting with respect to note taking
making sure they don't miss anything
we'll move on to the next topic which is
around the next mode of communication
which is around internet messaging so
tools like teams or slack which has
become increasingly popular
how effective do you find using iron for
communicating and what scenarios would
you use RM for your communication I
think it's extremely effective in the
the right contexts I think
It's very effective for the more nuanced
something is I think maybe the less
effective asynchronous communication is
and the reason for that is just that
it's so long especially you know one of
the benefits of asynchronous is time
zones one of the downsides is having a
nuanced discussion across time zones can
literally take days and so sometimes you
just have to say you know what we don't
have three days to go back and forth
um over multiple time zones and kind of
figure this out we should just have a
call for 10 minutes and figure it out so
I think that it is for Less nuanced
communication that can be facilitated
over multiple time zones I think it can
be very effective you know I'm in I mean
I don't even know how many slide
channels I'm in but a lot of them slack
is my kind of asynchronous communication
mode of choice but I also use it you
know when I'm coaching people we use
Google Docs and a lot of the reason for
that is you know we're a lot of the
things that I deliver for my clients are
for example emails or scripts and things
like that and asynchronously
communicating through those things is
actually extremely effective because we
can make comments and notes in the
document itself and so that's not iming
per se but we do use comments which
looks like I am if you zoom out enough
that it can be really effective because
we're in line in the context itself and
so the Nuance actually kind of lends
itself to that Medium whereas if you're
having like a business high level
business discussion in slack or teams or
or any of these tools if it's you know
tactical stuff when are we doing this
thing what is your opinion on this
that's great but if it's hey you know
what are our business objectives for Q3
next year it could take a long time to
have that conversation and really come
to an outcome in in slack so I love
asynchronous communication for you know
sharing information with people that
isn't critical information I don't think
it should be used for critical
information there are better ways to do
that especially if you're across time
zones that can be missed they may have
do not disturb on there's a lot of ways
that stuff can be missed if it's
critical and that's just not the medium
for it but for sort of a low impact easy
to discuss non-nuanced things then I
think asynchronous communication is
great because I can get to it when I get
to it right and so if you say hey let's
have a zoom call like I said earlier now
you and I the only thing I'm doing is
having that Zoom call that's all I can
do I can't do other stuff I can't finish
this task I was doing I have to be on
the zoom call whereas if it's an
asynchronous thing you say hey what do
you think a b or c then I can just get
to that whenever if it's not critical
and it's fine now I have five minutes in
between meetings I'll just answer that
question real quick and so it allows for
a lot more flexibility so I've always
been a big fan of asynchronous
communication whatever the medium for
stuff like that because it doesn't
distract you can use it to fill in gaps
in time that you have and just answer
questions that way as opposed to you
know kind of forcing things in where
they don't belong or using the wrong
medium for a meeting so to answer your
question I'm a big fan of slack I
wouldn't use it for you know critical
stuff I wasn't wouldn't use it for
extremely nuanced conversations but for
asynchronous stuff that's pretty easy to
discuss I think it's great because it
allows everybody to sort of take that
task when they can take it and leave it
until the time is good for them to get
to it
how do you ensure the effectiveness of
slack or teams to ensure that the
members understand you know it says
asynchronous so they don't need to jump
and drop everything and respond
immediately to your query on Slack
I think that's a really tough one so
I'll do I think this comes down to sort
of like personal tactics right one thing
is just as a matter of sort of company
or team culture just making sure that
people understand that so the things
that I just said for example would be
good things to do in like an all hands
meeting and just say Hey listen just so
you know team does is not for business
critical stuff so if you send somebody a
message on teams assume that it could
take them a little while to respond and
so that can help to sort of level set at
the culture and figure out you know to
make sure people are just aware of the
fact that you know I'm not necessarily
sitting there waiting on a notification
in teams or slack also personally I do a
thing I do this all the time where I'll
have a question for somebody it might
even be kind of a nuanced question but
it's not urgent and so you know I know
the best way is to get it in front of
them so that they can think about it and
I'll start with you know in all caps
this is not urgent and then I'll ask
them the question so sometimes you know
when you're thinking Hmm I'm gonna ping
this person in slack how do I make sure
that they don't drop what they're doing
I a good way to do that is just to start
with not urgent in caps like let them
know you do not need to respond to this
right now I do the same thing in email
by the way so I'll send an email pretty
frequently and I'll start it with hey
just so you know this is not urgent
answer this whenever you can and then
you of course you have to give them the
freedom to do that you can't just ping
them an hour later and say hey did you
see the thing because then you're kind
of contradicting yourself so I think
there are two layers to this one of them
is sort of corporately just kind of
explaining what the different media are
for they're using to communicate and you
know when is the time to use this medium
when is the time not to or to use a
different medium and then personally you
can kind of emphasize to people this is
not urgent I like to do that I'm a big
fan of that because then when I do have
something that's urgent they will know
it I'll say hey if you could answer this
as quickly as possible that's great and
people will answer me quickly because I
never say that unless it really is
urgent and otherwise I'm usually telling
them this is not urgent don't drop
anything just get back to me when you
can and so I think that's just a good
kind of policy in general is to sort of
let people know what's the level of
urgency and of course to to Silo the
level of urgency of your communication
into the appropriate Communication
channel so that you're not asking for
super urgent things on an asynchronous
thing like slack and instead you're
moving to you know whatever would be the
best way to communicate that it could be
a phone call or it could be an email or
whatever it is but just making sure that
you're using the right medium first and
then second communicating the level of
urgency so that they know whether they
need to really pay attention right now
and drop what they're doing or they can
finish this task and check it after
lunch right it almost seems like there's
a hierarchy of communication modes based
on no agency you start off with picking
up the phone if it's super urgent
and move down to maybe email or slack
and then move down to meetings what
would your view be about that hierarchy
how would you stack the various modes of
communication I think your hierarchy is
pretty good I think it will really be
dependent on
you know a lot of things so there's
something you didn't mention which is
like physically walking into someone's
office can be a pretty good way to
handle something urgent of course that
doesn't work in a world where a lot of
people work remotely right but I would
add that to the list too that might be
the highest urgency thing is that I'm in
my office I'm stuck on something it's
critically important that we resolve it
and I walk to your office which is you
know like I mentioned Zoom you're
focused on face to face if I walk into
your office now I'm in your like I'm I'm
in your physical space and you have to
acknowledge me and kind of talk to me so
that would be I think would be something
that would be reserved especially
unannounced I mean obviously you might
schedule an in-person meeting it's
totally different but you know showing
up unannounced in somebody's physical
space can be a way to communicate
significant urgency and so that would be
on the list too and I think those things
will kind of move around depending on
are you co-located or not are you
working across multiple time zones but I
think your hierarchy is pretty good I
mean in general maybe what I would do is
say instead of like pick up the phone or
in person there's like instantaneous
synchronous communication whatever that
looks like in your organization would be
like the highest level of urgency so
that could be walking into an office it
could be picking up a phone and then you
kind of slide down you know email is
asynchronous and in some places kind of
carries more weight than for example I
am and in some places it might carry
less weight and so I think that will
just depend on the organization itself
but internally most organizations have a
sense of like what that hierarchy looks
like in terms of what is the urgency
associated with each medium of
communication and I think the important
thing is to be intentional about the way
that you do it but I would start with
you know most urgent would be
synchronous unprompted synchronous
communication would be the highest level
of urgency and then all the way down to
sort of you know casual asynchronous
communication for things that that don't
matter very much and understanding how
your organization categorizes those
things is probably the the way that I
would you know take the next step there
and figure out like how should we be
doing this right we'll move on to emails
and what are some of the best practices
while using emails as a mode of
communication yeah I like email it's so
interesting right like I think that I
mean I don't even know how long email
has been around I think the 70s or the
80s or something like that so it's been
around for literal decades and my guess
is that if you talk to somebody in like
1975 I think there was email back then
and you told them you know you asked
them like hey how prominent is email
going to be as a communication method 50
years from now they would I don't know I
don't know what they would say my guess
is they would think but there's probably
something better right and yet I think
that email is still kind of the dominant
form of communication in a lot of
contexts which is really fascinating to
me so that's a that's kind of a side
topic but I think that best practices
for email especially in a business
context are you know you start with the
subject so that's where I started that's
where mastering business email starts
actually is the subject and so the whole
purpose of the subject of an email it
has one purpose and that is to get the
person to identify that it's something
they care about and open the email
that's all the subject is doing
obviously there are good ways to do that
in bad ways you know you could email
somebody with a subject your house is on
fire Exclamation point Exclamation point
and they're going to open it 100 of the
time if it's from someone they know if
they believe you as a person would say
that but if the inside is like hey what
are you doing for dinner tonight that's
a misalignment if you're subject to the
email so you want to choose a good
subject the first purpose of the subject
is to get the email to be opened at all
the second one I think is to be
discoverable later so I think this is
something that's sort of Lost in
business Communications especially over
email is that one reason I think it's so
dominant today is that you know I can go
into just the Gmail web app and I can
search my emails going back for decades
if I want to right like they're all
there and so I think it's most important
to have a good subject because you know
if I need to reference this conversation
three years from now
future me will be very happy if I used a
good subject line that is descriptive so
I can see exactly what this email is
about so I can find it trivially so the
first purpose of the subject is to get
the email opened the second one is to be
discoverable later on inside the email
for Best Practices I think it's best to
assume that people reading emails are
reading them very quickly or skimming
them if at all and so that I think lends
itself to doing two things one is to
make sure that you have a clear purpose
for the email so again this goes back to
we talked about this at the very
beginning of our conversation you should
have a reason for a meeting you should
have a reason for a business
communication there needs to be a reason
behind it and it's important for the
person who's doing the communicating to
actually
understand that reason and to kind of
adhere to it it's just good business
practice to say what is the purpose of
this email that I'm sending if you can't
answer that question then you probably
should stop and think about whether you
even need to send the email or if your
thoughts are well formed enough to send
it so you have a specific purpose and
that purpose should be easily and
quickly discoverable in the email and so
I think there are two ways to do that
one of them is through the formatting a
lot of what I talk about in mastering
business email is is formatting emails
to be skimmable again assuming that
people get hundreds of emails a day
which they do especially in business you
know I think I used to send when I was a
project manager somewhere between 100
and 200 emails a day that's not to
mention you know how many I got inbound
but outbound that's how many emails I'm
sending some of them are very short some
of them are longer but that's kind of
the job of a lot of people is emailing
for different purposes so it's important
that when they're looking through that
email first they see a subject and say
yep I know what this is this is for me
I'm going to open it then when they open
the email they very quickly are able to
discover what it is that they're
supposed to take away from the the email
two ways to do that one is formatting so
using good bullet points using bold text
to emphasize certain things making sure
to explicitly call out action items so
that all of these things are kind of
designed around the idea of making it
just extremely explicit what is going on
in the email and what it's for the worst
kind of email to get is like a single
giant paragraph that's like 15 lines
long that isn't clear who it's for or
what it's saying or what the action
items are what's going to happen is
you're just going to end up with a bunch
of people not reading that email and if
there is a critical action item buried
in there it's not going to get done and
that's on the person who sent the email
so I think you know formatting it so
that's easy to skim it also a nice rule
of thumb that I have is for whatever
reason the way that I write emails is
sometimes I tend to put the actual most
important thing at the very end as I'm
summarizing the email and so one little
tip that I like to suggest is after you
finish writing an email you formatted it
really well you've called out the ash
Adams scan the email look down at the
bottom and see if maybe the last
paragraph shouldn't be the first
paragraph because a lot of times it'll
be like and these are the reasons that I
think that we need to shift to this new
platform right and really that should be
the opening to the email hey everyone
here are some reasons that I think we
should shift to this new platform reason
one reason two reason three whereas I
buried that at the bottom so make sure
you don't bury the lead at the bottom of
the email and make sure that it's very
easy to read and understand and then
calling out action items very clearly I
think is important it's one thing to
inform people it's another thing that if
they have something they need to do you
need to make it very clear so that they
can see it you know skimming the email
for literally three seconds and see oh I
have an action here and they can take
that action and understand what to do
next so those are kind of my overarching
thoughts on business email and I'm happy
to dig in say anything there if anything
kind of resonated with you or or you can
move on absolutely I think quite a few
golden nuggets over there so just to
summarize first US make sure the subject
calls over the purpose so that the
person receiving it opens the email
that's super important the second one is
to make sure it's discoverable so that
you can if you if you want to search for
the email afterwards you can easily find
it I think the third point that you make
which is assume people's game over
emails is very important person writing
the email might have spent a lot of time
composing it but not everybody reads
that entire email it's you know long
form articles are not in style people
don't take the time to read a very long
email even though it might be covering a
lot of points and I like your rule of
thumb which is you know whatever you're
trying to convey the key action or the
key message bring it to the top rather
than leave it at the end because the
reader or the recipient might not reach
the end of the email before he he or she
jumps into something else
yeah I think that's a great summary I
think if people follow those guidelines
for writing email they'll find that it's
a lot more effective I mean that's what
I'm always thinking about is how to make
stuff maximally effective and I think
the guidelines that you just summarized
there very well if everyone does that
then business email suddenly becomes a
lot more effective it takes a lot less
time from people you know writing a good
email takes a while there's a I think it
might be apocryphal but I think it was
attributed to Mark Twain who says I was
going to write you a short letter but I
didn't have time so I wrote you a long
one instead it's really hard to write
succinct skimmable emails where the
action item is obvious it takes a lot of
effort and it is a learned skill but I
think it is worth learning understanding
that if you do that well then the person
who receives it in the 20 seconds that
they're going to give to you can totally
understand exactly what they need to do
what Their action items are what they
need to understand and they can move on
so that's part of the the gift of
writing a good email to someone else is
that they don't have to spend a lot of
time digesting it and like I said later
on you might be searching for that so
it's really important to remember number
email is kind of infinitely discoverable
over the long run and so a lot of the
emails I send for my clients are meant
to be written as a communicating
something but also to make sure that
later when this is looked at by someone
else that's very clear what's going on
here it's not ambiguous and so I think
it's important you know whereas slack
message and things like that they're
they're more or less ephemeral they're
just kind of going to go away Zoom
meetings usually you're not recording
them that's going to go away but email
is usually you know it's more of a kind
of a permanent document which is sort of
weird but it's the way it is so make
sure that when you go back to look at
that in two years and try and figure out
why did we decide to change platforms
there's an email that says here are the
reasons we should change platforms and
in ABC and then there's somebody
responding saying I think you know
region B really resonates with me we
should do it and you can find that
really easily in email which is you know
sort of a just a discoverable historical
document that's going to be out there
forever you also brought up another
interesting point which is when you were
in your previous role as a project
manager you used to send a lot of emails
in the hundreds
and that is the question I wanted to ask
about managing email overload so in
addition to those emails that you
receive from people a lot of emails that
I receive are automated emails saying
that the build is successful or it's
failed uh cicd comments request to
review peers and so on how do you manage
email overload this is a really
interesting topic to me because I do not
think that there is like a a best
practice here I think it's it's personal
preference so there are a few ways to do
this the way that I do it actually is I
use you know the Gmail app on my phone
and as soon as I see something come in I
just archive it right away unless
there's like a specific action time
before it or I snooze it right and so
I'm an inbox zero kind of person a lot
of people just cannot do that I
understand that so my second suggestion
will be more for them but I think just
my rule of thumb is I just deal with it
right away I get it I read it if I'm
gonna have to take action on it later I
will snooze it or do whatever I need to
do if I don't need to take action on it
it's just an FYI I'll just archive it
right away I also think that it depends
on your email client but nowadays most
email clients have you know labels or
folders and stuff like that so I think
one thing I would do especially with
those automated pull request emails and
stuff unless you actually need to review
all of those emails and understand them
or like you said like deployment status
emails and stuff I would just set up you
know a label people in Gmail or folder I
think is what they use in Outlook and
just have it immediately shunted over to
that place just get it out of my inbox I
need you to see it and so that's a lot
of it is understanding do I even need to
see that email and the same goes for
like you know a lot of our email even in
business context a lot of our inboxes
like newsletters and stuff like that for
products that we signed up for or
whatever it is that we're kind of signed
up for and I find that like I just need
to go through every now and then just
unsubscribe from a bunch of newsletters
because I don't need that in my inbox
and even just being distracted by this
thing coming in my inbox and it's like I
have I haven't even opened an email from
this company in six months why am I
still getting emails from them so I
think that's you know the so the high
level is try to make sure that the stuff
that actually appears in your inbox is
stuff that you need to know is there so
all the automated stuff that comes from
you know deployment and CI and like
GitHub emails unless you really need to
see them just send them off somewhere
else put them into a folder put a label
on them so they don't show up in your
inbox unsubscribe from stuff that you
don't need to be subscribed to
especially you know if you realize you
haven't even opened that email in months
and months you probably should just
unsubscribe from it you can always go
back and get it later if you ever think
you know I wonder what happened to that
company and the the SAS product I was
kind of looking at you just go find out
so yeah top of top of funnel I would say
is important there keep the stuff that
actually comes into your inbox to a
minimum use the labels and filters
liberally if you're comfortable doing
that and then also just archive stuff or
get it out of your inbox as quickly as
possible if it's not something that you
need to act on and that should hopefully
kind of bring it down to now you're
looking at emails that you actually need
to know about that you need to take some
kind of an action on my rule of thumb
for those emails is if I can do it
really quickly assuming that I'm not you
know inflow if I'm not you know writing
code or writing you know an article or
you know doing something that requires
my focus in which case I probably
shouldn't be looking at my inbox but if
I am looking at my inbox if I could just
knock it out in like 20 seconds if it's
you know go go check this box or you
know send this other email to somebody
I'll just knock it out right away that's
a personal preference again get it out
of your focus so it can no longer
distract you and try and take care of
that little stuff first and that will
leave you know the bigger items that
need to be to be wrestled with and
that's where you have to start kind of
like prioritizing your time and maybe
using some other medium a checklist or
to Do's or just managing your own
workload to figure out like how do I
accomplish the things that are coming
into my inbox so again I'll emphasize I
do not think there's a best practice
here I have made some suggestions there
but I think different people kind of
navigate email very differently and
there's not a best way to do it there's
a best for you way to do it and those
are the things that I do to try to kind
of keep my my inbox managed
moving on to a tool which is universally
used and hated by almost everybody who
uses it as PowerPoint presentations what
are the common mistakes made when
somebody presents or creates a
presentation
I mean the most common mistake that I
see is just way too much information on
the slides themselves sometimes you have
to put a lot of information there
especially if you're showing you know
charts for quarterly earnings or
something right so CFOs maybe maybe
don't listen to me right now but for
most people if you're doing a
presentation you're probably presenting
to an audience who needs to know kind of
generally what you're talking about you
might be teaching them something or you
might just be conveying some basic
information the PowerPoint presentation
itself is not the information it is a
tool to help you to communicate that
information and so you know the rule of
thumb is you know one slide per minute I
think I'm fine with that I could go you
know over under on that but keep the
actual stuff on the slide
to a minimum so you know three or four
words or one or two bullet points or one
image and try to keep the number of
slides to a minimum because again if
you're using the PowerPoint as the thing
that actually communicates the
information you're probably using that
Medium ineffectively I would say there
are better ways to communicate a lot of
information an email is one of them a
white paper is one of them but I think
that the words that you're saying are
what you're communicating and so the the
PowerPoint is just a way to facilitate
that and maybe add some context in some
cases so you're describing something and
now there's a chart on the screen that
shows the thing that you're describing
that can be very helpful but if you have
you know 15 bullet points or you're
using 16 point font on a slide it's
probably got too much information on it
and the problem with that is I think
people just tune out like I if I see a
slide that has a ton of information on
it I'm not looking at it I'm not going
to sit there and read the 12 bullet
points on the slide I just won't do it
and so you have one bullet point or two
bullet points you have five words ten
words of one picture and try to used a
lower number of slides to try to
communicate in fewer slides not their
exceptions to this I have a friend Keith
who is very very very good at public
speaking and he'll do a PowerPoint
presentation with like 150 slides where
it's literally just bang bang but it's
because his presentation style lends
itself to it most people can't pull that
off I think he might be the only person
I know that can pull it off so for most
people I would say fewer slides fewer
words on each slide just less stuff and
make sure that you understand that what
you're communicating is not a PowerPoint
presentation if I build a PowerPoint
presentation and I could just send you
the presentation you don't need me to
present it then I think something went
wrong somewhere I should have written an
article or a blog post or sent you a
book or written a white paper and so
that the purpose of the PowerPoint is
it's supposed to facilitate like a live
presentation so I think keeping those
things in mind will really help make
PowerPoint presentations better and have
people actually pay attention to what
you're doing and also just make people
better public speakers PowerPoint is a
tool to help speak publicly I think it
should be used that way and not as an
actual medium to communicate information
which is not really what it's designed
for right interesting thoughts and very
useful tips
moving on from the modes of
communication I'd like to talk about
cross-cultural communication especially
now in the current setup where we have
teams which are distributed across
geographies what are the key
considerations when you are
communicating with individuals from
different cultures different
geographies in a business setting
I think one thing is just to be very
careful sort of how you're communicating
I think so I'll use like uh the us as an
example right even if I'm communicating
with people that are in different parts
of the US like there are things that I
would say that I would consider to be a
joke or an idiom that won't register
with other people they just won't even
understand it and so I think it's
important in cases where the differences
in kind of cultural understanding of the
specific words that we use are high then
just being more explicit and more direct
is better this can be taken overboard
and so you know Engineers sometimes can
kind of err on the side of being too
direct and so there is some Nuance there
but I think in general just ask yourself
you know is the way that I'm phrasing
this going to be understood by the
person who is reading what I'm writing
and so I think with written
Communication in particular across
cultures that that's the best way to do
it is to keep it simple keep it direct
use words that are understood by
everyone I think you can be a little bit
more nuanced on for example a phone call
because a lot of times you know the tone
tone of your voice and other cues that
you give will help to communicate that
you're actually telling a joke or you're
being sarcastic or here's what you
actually mean but if you're writing
something down and you're communicating
with somebody from a different culture I
think it's important to just be be
direct the caveat I would put on that is
I've had a number of conversations with
friends who run firms where they have
engineers and sales people those are
kind of cultures too right engineering
culture is different than sales culture
it's different than Finance culture and
so I think understanding you know well
we're talking about cross-cultural
communication sometimes we're not
talking about you know Geographic
distance we're talking about sort of
work function difference different
cultures of work function and I think
the same things apply there where it's
like you know an inside joke for a sales
guy might be completely missed by
somebody in engineering and vice versa
and so I think in those cases again it's
it's important to just be direct and
communicate directly what you mean and
the less personal the communication so
for example you know asynchronous
communication on teams then the more
direct it should be and I think there
could be a little bit more nuance and
you know more personal communication and
or you're you know synchronously
communicating in person you know I'm
sitting down across a table from you and
we're talking you can learn so much more
about what I mean by watching my body
language and seeing my face and hearing
the tone of my voice and the Cadence of
with which I'm speaking whereas you know
in slack all of that stuff is not
available all you can see is the literal
words that I write and so I think it's
more important to be direct there the
the a caveat I would add also is try to
be positive so direct can also come
across as very harsh especially in
writing and so what I mean is you know
direct might be you missed your target
please do better next time that's direct
however it's not very kind and in in
writing in particular it can come across
as very harsh you know if I say that to
you in person I can say Hey you missed
your target let's do better next time
and then we can talk about that right
and that's a very it sounds like I'm not
coming down on you I'm just
acknowledging something that was amiss
and we're going to talk about how to fix
it whereas if I write that you know
asynchronously you miss your target
please do better next time man that
seems really harsh and so I think using
positive language which is something I
talk a lot about is super important
where you know you find a way to say
things in a positive way so rather than
you miss your target you might say let's
see if we can find ways to improve the
way that we're performing this business
function so that we can make the target
next time it's a little bit more wordy
it's a little bit indirect but it will
come across as less mean and
asynchronous kind of written
communication and so using positive
words can kind of help bridge that Gap
so cross-cultural communication is a big
challenge I mean it's becoming more and
more of a challenge like I said
geographically but also in terms of
business functions you know business
functions are overlapping more and more
these days a lot of people are
communicating with people they wouldn't
have communicated with before and so I
think you know defaults being direct and
trying to use positive language when you
can those are my kind of two rules of
Thumbs right and how can one navigate
potential language barriers
so if you have people who are based on a
non-english speaking native
English-speaking country the grammar
might not be right and that might imply
that you know the message does not get
conveyed correctly how do you navigate
such situations yeah I think a lot of
that is if the parties are being direct
then the grammar is sort of less
meaningful I think and I think also I
mean I had a number of jobs where I
worked with people globally frequently
people from India but also people from
countries in the UK and you know Germany
for example in other countries like that
where you know we're not communicating
in everyone's first language whatever
that is and so I think just
understanding that it's really hard to
learn languages any language has a lot
of nuance to it and I think just kind of
giving some Grace for that is the way to
go I mean there's there's not like a
really tactical way to do it but if I'm
communicating with somebody who I know
is they're communicating with me in
English because I can't speak their
language first of all and so they're
communicating with me in my language
which is a benefit to me that they have
learned my language and they use
something that that appears to be
grammar that isn't quite right unless
it's a huge deal right unless they're
writing like for example if they're
client facing that might be something we
should work on because the client might
perceive you know a different level of
Engagement or knowledge or quality or
whatever those things are because the
grammar doesn't align with a job
function but internal Communications I
think it's you know you just kind of
have to say that person is doing me a
favor by speaking a language that I
understand so that I don't have to learn
their language maybe I don't need to
nitpick their grammar and so internally
I think you just kind of have to accept
it it's just part of the fact that we're
doing business globally and then like I
said if the person is going to be
communicating with a client I think you
know maybe correct grammar is more
important there and that's where you
know we talk about like how can we help
this person become better with grammar
or possibly have them communicate
through an intermediary or somebody who
can summarize or something like that so
the client perceives you know a high
level of understanding of what's going
on so I think you know I think most
people Now understand that just because
someone doesn't use the correct grammar
doesn't mean they don't know what
they're talking about but you know you
always want to be kind of as polished as
you can be when communicating with
clients I will say we're talking about
grammar here but there are a lot of
people who are communicating with
clients who speak perfect English and
are doing it poorly and so I think you
know in general that's something that I
should be on a company's radar
especially when they have customer
facing roles that they're doing
consulting or have a customer service or
something it's important to help them to
understand how to communicate with
clients not only with the correct
grammar with the right words and the
right Cadence and the right tone and the
right level of helpfulness so that those
customers feel like they're getting a
lot of value for whatever they're doing
there so you know grammar is one thing
but there's a lot of other things about
communication where people don't do it
quite right and it can be a quality
signal whether it's actually a real
signal or not then what strategies can
help build trust and rapper with
colleagues from different cultural
backgrounds
I think that's another thing that's
extremely challenging one is just to
understand that you are from different
backgrounds which means you're going to
be different people and then I think
like I said this is where the the
positive language thing that I mentioned
earlier kind of comes into is like if
you're more kind to people they will be
more kind to you in general and it will
facilitate more relaxed conversations
and so if somebody communicates with you
and they use grammar that isn't quite
right and you call them on it every time
even though it doesn't really matter
that person is probably going to have a
hard time connecting with you on a
personal level or being friendly with
you because they're afraid that when
they try to do that you're just gonna
nitpick them so I think that it's
important to just try to be to show
Grace there and then to connect with
them by just being a human a human being
and this is where even the occasional
sort of synchronous phone call or Zoom
meeting can be really beneficial is
building that culture so that you are
comfortable talking to someone it's
amazing how you know even you and I are
our first conversation as we kind of
prepared for this podcast and did some
technical stuff was a face-to-face
communication and I felt like I went
from somebody who had communicated with
you quite a bit over email to talking
face to face and now we're not face to
face but we're having a great
conversation and I feel like I know you
really well from that one pretty short
person-to-person face-to-face
conversation that we had and so I think
that that's something that companies
should be looking for is you know are
there opportunities where we can do a
synchronous meeting even once or twice a
year that's 10 minutes even so that
these people who work together
frequently can actually see each other
and know each other better and I think
that will make a lot of those
Communications easier because it makes
the person more human as opposed to just
you know a person on the other side of a
handle on slack is a lot different than
the person that I spoke with face to
face on Zoom yesterday so I think you
know showing Grace understanding that
different cultures are just different
and we're not like other people and
other people are not necessarily like us
and again this is I'm talking Geographic
but also business functions where people
are just different acknowledging that
and leaning into it embracing it and
then also trying to find ways to sort of
demystify who that person is can I think
be a huge help there and that's that's a
place where I am a fan of a phone call
every now and then or a face-to-face
Zoom meeting
right and very interesting example here
that that rings are true with me the
last one the question that I wanted to
move on to was not a mode of
communication but something which AIDS
communication and wanted to know your
thoughts and some strategies around
active listening how does one improve
active listening what does it mean maybe
you start off over there and move on to
some tips and tools for our listeners to
improve their listening skills
first let me say I think active
listening might have like a technical
definition which I'm not aware of I'm
aware of the idea so I just want to be
clear that if somebody's listening and
they're like actually kind of educated
on active listening as a technique I'm
probably not going to get it right but
I'll tell you what I think of when I
think of active listening and that is
one just being engaged so what I mean by
that though is maybe different than what
you might perceive so I've said a lot of
things in this conversation that are
kind of breadcrumbs for this particular
Trail and that is being engaged doesn't
necessarily mean making perfect eye
contact the entire time that you're
listening what it means is that you are
doing whatever you need to do to take in
what the person is saying and process it
by hearing the words that they're saying
and what they're trying to communicate
and so we've talked about you know on
zoom and how I think that can actually
hinder my ability to listen actively
because I'm not my part of my brain is
focused on making good eye contact with
a camera and wondering if my lighting is
okay whereas you know I mentioned I'm
kind of a Pacer and so if I'm having a
phone call with somebody we're talking
about something nuanced I will free
frequently not be at my desk I'll put in
my airpods and I'll just wander around
my house or my office and try to listen
carefully to what they're saying and
that helps me to actively listen because
it for whatever reason kind of moving
around helps me to process it some
people like to take notes I'm the
opposite of that right we talked about
note-taking so I think for you what you
said earlier I think that taking notes
for you might be part of active
listening whereas for me it would not be
active listening I would not be hearing
what the person says so I think in
general if you're going to actively
listen it's going to be you're doing
whatever you need to do to hear and
understand and process what the person
that is speaking to you is saying and
importantly I think not just thinking
about what your response is to what
they're saying so this is a habit that I
have and other people have pretty
frequently when you're having
conversations is instead of listening to
the words that you're saying I'm
thinking about what my response is going
to be when I have an opportunity to talk
and I'm counting down the seconds until
I have a window to say what my opinion
is on this thing which means I'm
probably not really getting what you're
saying a lot of the time I've already
formulated an opinion I'm going to go
ahead and say it as soon as I get the
opportunity and now I'm just waiting on
the window to open so I can say my you
know my genius thought that I have
that's not active listening because I'm
not really processing what you're saying
I may not even be open to changing what
I would have planned to say depending on
what you say so I think that first and
foremost it's important to make sure
that you're actually listening to the
words that they say and processing what
their intent is what they're trying to
accomplish trying to sympathize with
what they're saying in their perspective
so that you can see whether you agree or
disagree in the beginning to formulating
thoughts on the other side I think tools
for that are going to vary by person for
like I said earlier taking notes might
be a good tool to help somebody active
listen it might help them to focus it
might help them to make sure they don't
miss anything and it might help them to
formulate their own thoughts whereas for
me taking notes is a distraction so for
me active listening is pacing around my
house listening on the phone and
processing that way and trying to
respond to them I also think a really
good thing to do in context especially
where you have like a verbal meeting if
there are things being discussed is to
listen carefully and then afterwards to
summarize those things back so a lot of
my emails that I sent as a project
manager and that I send now to my
clients are hey here's what we talked
about bullet point bullet point bullet
point so that's not necessarily active
listening but I have to listen actively
to get those things and to be able to
summarize the meaning that carefully and
so I think you know sending a quick
summary can help with that because it's
another opportunity to process what you
talked about to make sure that you were
listening well enough to get those
summaries the the notes and to send them
back I also think for some people
recording conversations might be helpful
occasionally recording a zoom call can
be really good if you're afraid that
you're going to miss some Nuance or
something like that so I think active
listening ultimately comes down to
paying attention making sure that you're
processing what the other person is
saying and that you're not already out
ahead of them thinking about what your
response is going to be to what you
think they're going to say that can be a
great way to miss a lot of nuance and to
miss what they actually are trying to
communicate and maybe even just get it
wrong and so I think you know being
present focused on what they're saying
and doing whatever you have to do to
make sure that you internalize their
words and process them well to
understand their intent and then to
engage with them is how I would approach
active listening in general
excellent we covered a lot of ground
here was there anything we missed that
you would like to mention Josh
I don't think so you know I mentioned
positive language very briefly and
that's something that I I would
encourage I think it's kind of a life
hack for people and and so I would
encourage you if you're and the reason
this comes to mind for me is that it's
good for any medium of communication so
think about the thing that you're saying
and then ask yourself if there's a way
to say it using positive words instead
of negative one so if you say I'm sorry
you didn't get the assignment that's
sort of negative but what you might say
instead is we're going to go a different
direction on this assignment with
someone else and I want to work with you
to find a way to prepare you for the
next assignment that comes along right
they're subtly different but I think
that if you if you think about how to
use positive words it kind of solves a
lot of the problems that we've talked
about with cross-cultural communication
with being heard with getting your
message across with getting a response
from people which is a lot when we
talked about email I mean a lot of the
purpose of it is to get it read and to
get them to do the thing and you'll get
a lot more people to listen to what you
have to say if you're using positive
language especially as you're being more
direct right right with asynchronous
communication we talked about being more
direct more direct doesn't necessarily
mean terse or negative it means explicit
and you can be explicit with somebody
and make sure they understand what
you're communicating while also being
kind and using positive words and so in
general I think just the filter for that
is what's this thing I'm about to say
are there negative words in it like
can't won't shouldn't didn't and can I
replace those words with words that are
positive and how do I rephrase it so
that's a positive message that I'm
sending which will keep people engaged
longer it will help them to internalize
it it will make them less defensive and
I think we'll get better results in the
long run I must say this has been a
master class on business communication
for me Josh thank you for coming on the
show it's been a real pleasure this is
prediction modern for software
engineering jtu thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign